MARCOS DÍAZ GAY

San Diego, CA (USA) • mdiazgay@health.ucsd.edu • orcid.org/oooo-ooo3-o658-o467

SUMMARY

I am a postdoctoral researcher in the group of Prof. Ludmil B. Alexandrov at the University of California, San Diego. Originally trained in engineering, I have focused my career on computational biology, with a strong interest in cancer genomics data analysis. My research focuses on developing new computational methodologies that allow the discovery of the underlying mechanisms of cancer predisposition and progression. Making this knowledge accessible to the research community and understanding the dynamics and evolution of human cancer are my main goals at the Alexandrov lab.

CURRENT POSITION

University of California, San Diego POSTDOCTORAL SCHOLAR (Alexandrov lab)

Feb 2020 – present Main project: "Mutational signatures dynamics in human cancers".

EXPERIENCE

August Pi i Sunyer Biomedical Research PhD STUDENT (Genetic Predisposition to Gastrointestinal Cancer group)

Institute PhD thesis: "Identification of new candidate genes for germline predisposition to familial

Aug 2016 – Nov 2019 colorectal cancer using somatic mutational profiling".

University of California, San Diego VISITING GRADUATE STUDENT (Alexandrov lab)

Feb 2019 – May 2019 VGS project: "Advanced detection of mutational signatures in colorectal cancer".

August Pi i Sunyer Biomedical Research MSc STUDENT (Genetic Predisposition to Gastrointestinal Cancer group)

Institute MSc thesis: "Identification of novel genes involved in familial colorectal cancer: integrated

Nov 2015 – Jul 2016 analysis of germline and tumor DNA".

University of A Coruña RESEARCH ASSISTANT (Water and Environmental Engineering group)

Dec 2013 – Jul 2015

EDUCATION

University of Barcelona PhD | MEDICINE AND TRANSLATIONAL RESEARCH

2016 - 2019

University of Barcelona / MSc | BIOINFORMATICS AND BIOSTATISTICS

Open University of Catalonia In progress (67 % completed).

2017 – present

University of Barcelona MSc | BIOMEDICINE

2015 - 2016

University of A Coruña BSc & MSc | CIVIL ENGINEERING

2009 - 2015

PUBLICATIONS

Total number of publications: 17 (1 preprint) | Citations: 237 (Google scholar), 154 (WOS) | h-index: 9 (Google scholar), 8 (WOS)

Original articles as first author

Uncovering novel mutational signatures by de novo extraction with SigProfilerExtractor

Islam S.M.A.*, **Díaz-Gay M.*** et al. BioRxiv. 2022:12.13.422570 (preprint).

*shared first authors

Using linkage studies combined with whole-exome sequencing to identify novel candidate genes for familial colorectal cancer Toma C.*, **Díaz-Gay M.*** et al. International Journal of Cancer. 2020;146(6):1568–1577.

Identification of a novel candidate gene for serrated polyposis syndrome by performing linkage analysis combined with whole-exome sequencing

Toma C.*, **Díaz-Gay M.*** et al. Clinical and Translational Gastroenterology. 2019;10(10):e00100.

Integrated analysis of germline and tumor DNA identifies new candidate genes involved in familial colorectal cancer Díaz-Gay M. et al. Cancers. 2019;11(3):362.

Mutational signatures in cancer (MuSiCa): a web application to implement mutational signatures analysis in cancer samples Díaz-Gay M. et al. BMC Bioinformatics. 2018;19(1):224.

Reviews and book chapters as first author

Unraveling the genomic landscape of colorectal cancer through mutational signatures [book chapter]

Díaz-Gay M. & Alexandrov L.B. Advances in Cancer Research: "Novel Approaches to Colorectal Cancer". 2021;151:385-424.

Somatic mutational signatures in polyposis and colorectal cancer [review]

Grolleman J.*, **Díaz-Gay M.*** et al. Molecular Aspects of Medicine. 2019;69:62–72.

Original articles in collaboration

Comprehensive genomic characterization of early-onset Lynch-like syndrome colorectal cancers

Golubicki M. et al. Cancers. 2021.;13(6):1259.

Germline and somatic WES identifies new candidate genes involved in familial predisposition to serrated polyposis syndrome

Soares de Lima Y. *et al. Cancers*. 2021;13(4):929.

Identification of new genes involved in germline predisposition to early-onset gastric cancer

Herrera-Pariente C. et al. International Journal of Molecular Sciences. 2021;22(3), 1310.

Germline biallelic mutations in MCM8 are associated with early-onset lynch-like syndrome

Golubicki M. et al. JCI Insight. 2020;5(18):e140698.

Germline mutations in FAF1 are associated with hereditary colorectal cancer

Bonjoch L. *et al. Gastroenterology*. 2020;159(1):227-240.

Colorectal cancer genetic variants are also associated with serrated polyposis syndrome susceptibility

Arnau-Collell C. et al. Journal of Medical Genetics. 2020;57(10):677-682.

CNApp, a tool for the quantification of copy number alterations and integrative analysis revealing clinical implications

Franch-Expósito S. et al. eLife. 2020;9:e50267.

Quantitative analysis of somatically-acquired and constitutive uniparental disomy in gastrointestinal cancers

Torabi K. et al. International Journal of Cancer. 2019;144(3):513–524.

Rare germline copy number variants in colorectal cancer predisposition characterized by exome sequencing analysis

Franch-Expósito S. et al. Journal of Genetics and Genomics. 2018;45(1):41-45.

POLE and POLD1 screening in 155 patients with multiple polyps and early-onset colorectal cancer

Esteban-Jurado C. et al. Oncotarget. 2017;8(16):26732-26743.

FUNDING, SCHOLARSHIPS & AWARDS

University of Barcelona CUM LAUDE HONORS (PhD)

Nov 2019 Faculty of Medicine.

University of Barcelona SHORT-TERM INTERNATIONAL RESEARCH STAY FELLOWSHIP

Dec 2018 Faculty of Medicine.

University of Barcelona EXTRAORDINARY MASTER'S DEGREE AWARD

Apr 2018 Faculty of Medicine.

Regional Government of Catalunya PhD FELLOWSHIP FI-2017

Feb 2017 Agency for Management of University and Research Grants (AGAUR).

University of A Coruña EXTRAORDINARY END-OF-DEGREE AWARD

Jan 2016 School of Civil Engineering.

SOFTWARE

Co-author and maintainer of <u>MuSiCa</u> R-Shiny web application and <u>SigProfilerExtractor</u> Python package for mutational signature analysis. Co-author and curator of the <u>COSMIC Mutational Signatures</u> website.

REFERENCES

Dr. Ludmil B. Alexandrov, PhD Cellular and Molecular Medicine and Bioengineering departments, University of California, San Diego. Moores Cancer Center, 3855 Health Sciences Dr, 92093 La Jolla, CA (United States of America). <a href="mailto:leaenground-color: blue color: blue color

Dr. Sergi Castellví-Bel, PhD Genetic Predisposition to Gastrointestinal Cancer group, August Pi i Sunyer Biomedical Research Institute (IDIBAPS), CIBERehd, Hospital Clínic. Rosselló 153, 08036 Barcelona (Spain). sbel@clinic.cat

Dr. Francesc Balaguer, MD, PhD Gastroenterology department, Hospital Clínic, CIBERehd, IDIBAPS. Villarroel 153, 08036 Barcelona (Spain). fprunes@clinic.cat